בוקר טוב, Boker tov, happy fifth day of Chanukah. We are on
דף יט, Daf Yud Tet, 19, but we pick up at the
bottom of יח עמוד ב. Yud Chet Amud Bet. We are now
transitioning to the final part of the משנה. Mishnah. I mean the
first משנה Mishnah was the whole משנה Mishnah of the פרק, perek,
like the same case in the first פרק, perek, which is really
like a printer's choice, but anyway, or publisher's choice. But we also
are going to, God willing, wrap up the פרק perek today and
move on to the third פרק, perek, which finally gets us on
the main topic of the מסכתא, masecheta, which is שבועות. Shevuot. But
the last thing is we circle back to the question of, or
about טומאת מקדש, Tumat Mikdash, and about bringing a קרבן עולה ויורד
Korban Oleh V'Yored of variable value sin-offering קרבן, korban, based on your
ability to afford it.
And you bring that when you, the basic שתים שהן ארבע shtayim
shehein arba is, if the Torah says ונעלם ממנו והוא טמא—it v'ne'elam
mimenu v'hu tamei was hidden from you and you were טמא. tamei.
So the simple sense of the פסוק pasuk is, is that you
were unaware that you were טמא, tamei, you were actually טמא, tamei,
then you did something wrong, you entered into the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash or ate a קרבן. korban. Those are the two scenarios. But
the ארבע arba is that you were aware that you were טמא,
tamei, but the other part was hidden from you. It was hidden
from you that what you were eating was a קרבן, korban, or
you didn't realize that you were entering into the בית המקדש. Beit
HaMikdash. Okay, so that's the extra two. But in the משנה, Mishnah,
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva rejects that. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva goes just
by the פשט pshat of the פסוק, pasuk, and he says only
העלם טומאה helam tumah you're חייב chayav a קרבן. korban. If it
was the other case, you didn't know that you were entering into
the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, then you do not bring a קרבן.
korban. It's funny, you're not a מזיד, meizid, so you don't get
any punishment in the court down here. You're a שוגג, shogeg, but
it's not the שוגג shogeg that the Torah is talking about, so
you don't bring a קרבן. korban. תוספות Tosafot actually puts out a
fascinating suggestion, I don't know if you'd call it a suggestion, opinion
of רבינו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, that you don't bring a קרבן עולה
ויורד, Korban Oleh V'Yored, but you bring a קרבן חטאת, Korban Chatat,
because you still did a sin that you're חייב כרת chayav kares
for. But that's not פשט pshat of any גמרא. Gemara. Okay, the
simple thing is somehow this guy falls between the cracks. Okay, he
doesn't bring an עולה ויורד, Oleh V'Yored, that's only for העלם טומאה,
helam tumah, he wasn't מזיד, meizid, he'll just have to do תשובה
teshuvah and יום כיפור Yom Kippur and whatever. Okay, so that's רבי
עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. But רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael disagrees with this, and
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael is the author of our משנה. Mishnah. And
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says only either העלם טומאה helam tumah or
העלם מקדש. helam mikdash. Now the משנה Mishnah ends before quoting רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael with the opinion, I mean actually before even quoting
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, it quotes
רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. רבי אליעזר אומר השרץ ונעלם ממנו, Rabbi Eliezer
omer ha-sheretz v'ne'elam mimenu, על העלם שרץ חייב. al helam sheretz chayav.
You're חייב chayav if you, it says, you know, if you don't
know you touched a שרץ. sheretz. If you don't know you touched
the object. Now רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says something that sounds almost
identical. He says על העלם טומאה—if al helam tumah you don't know
you're טמא. tamei. So both of them are saying the same point,
that the only time you bring a קרבן korban is if you're
not aware that you're טמא. tamei. If you're aware you're טמא tamei
and you're not aware you're entering the מקדש, Mikdash, you don't bring
a קרבן. korban. So the גמרא Gemara wants to know what is
the difference between רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva,
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer being רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva רבי. rebbe. So
let's take a look. It is three lines before the lines get
wide on יח עמוד ב. Yud Chet Amud Bet. רבי אליעזר אומר
השרץ ונעלם ממנו. Rabbi Eliezer omer ha-sheretz v'ne'elam mimenu. מאי בינייהו? Mai
beinaihu? What's the difference between saying העלם טומאה, helam tumah, which is
what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says, and העלם שרץ, helam sheretz, which
is what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says? Both talking about the same
thing. So אמר חזקיה שרץ ונבילה איכא בינייהו. Amar Chizkiyya sheretz v'neveilah
ika beinaihu. What they're dealing with is that the guy knows he's
טמא, tamei, but he doesn't know how he became טמא. tamei. Did
he become טמא tamei because he touched a שרץ, sheretz, or did
he become טמא tamei because he touched a נבילה neveilah of a
cow that was not slaughtered properly? So okay, who cares? Nobody cares.
But the question is when the Torah
says the פסוק pasuk in the Torah mentions in detail the types
of objects that a person might touch in this context to become
טמא. tamei. So right there in ויקרא, Vayikra, it says and, you
know, so the question is like it doesn't, you know, what do
we do? Look at the פסוקים, pesukim, we have to go with
what the פסוקים pesukim say. So the פסוקים pesukim say או נפש
כי תגע בכל דבר טמא—it o nefesh ki tiga b'chol davar tamei
could have ended there. But it says או בנבלת חיה טמאה או
בנבלת בהמה טמאה או בנבלת שרץ טמא ונעלם ממנו. o b'nivlat chayah
tmeiah, o b'nivlat behemah tmeiah, o b'nivlat sheretz tamei v'ne'elam mimenu. It
gives three concrete examples. So I understand. Well you know elsewhere what
makes you טמא, tamei, go look at the נזירות Nezirut or whatever,
I don't know Michael. Anyway, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says because it's
being specific and concrete, it means that what is required is that
you initially knew how you became טמא. tamei. Because remember, you always
need ידיעה בתחילה yedi'ah batchilah and then העלמה he'elamah and then to
forget. So that's נבלת שרץ טמא ונעלם. nivlat sheretz tamei v'ne'elam. What
has to be ונעלם ne'elam is not just that you're טמא, tamei,
but the concrete knowledge of how you became טמא, tamei, the specifics
of your טומאה. tumah. That's what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says. So
the גמרא Gemara says, alright, let's read it. רבי אליעזר סבר, Rabbi
Eliezer savar, okay,
שרץ ונבילה איכא בינייהו. sheretz v'neveilah ika beinaihu. שרץ sheretz and נבילה
neveilah are two cases mentioned exactly in the פסוקים. pesukim. So you
know you're טמא, tamei, you don't remember whether it was that you
touched the שרץ sheretz or you touched a נבילה. neveilah. And then
you forgot. Remember, you need ידיעה בתחילה yedi'ah batchilah and then העלמה
he'elamah and then to forget. So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would say
that's not legitimate העלמה. he'elamah. Yes, you don't know your... but you
need to have forgotten
that you were the... you need to have started with a concrete
ידיעה. yedi'ah. Okay, Rabbi Eliezer סבר בעינן עד ידע, savar be'inan ad
yeida, אי בשרץ אטמי אי בנבלה אטמי. ee b'sheretz itmei ee b'neveilah
itmei.
You have to start by knowing whether you became טמא tamei through
touching a שרץ sheretz or a נבלה neveilah specifically how you became
טמא tamei or whatever was the specific cause. Rabbi Akiva סבר לא
בעינן עד ידע. savar lo be'inan ad yeida. You don't know that.
וכיוון דידע דאטמי בעולם, v'keivan d'yada d'itmei b'olam, since you know that
you became טמא tamei somehow, that you were טמא, tamei, לא צריך
אי בשרץ אטמי אי בנבלה אטמי. lo tzarich ee b'sheretz itmei ee
b'neveilah itmei. You don't need to know whether it was through a
שרץ sheretz or a נבלה. neveilah. Okay, וכן אמר עולא. vechein amar
Ulla. עולא Ulla said the same explanation over here to eight. שרץ
ונבלה איכא בינייהו. Sheretz v'neveilah ika beinayhu.
Now, now how do you know that עולא Ulla read Rabbi Eliezer
that way? דעולא רמי דרבי אליעזר אדרבי אליעזר ומשני, d'Ulla rami d'Rabbi
Eliezer a'd'Rabbi Eliezer u'mishni, because we infer that from a different statement
of עולא Ulla where he actually showed that it looks like Rabbi
Eliezer contradicts himself and then he resolved the problem. So let's see
what the apparent contradiction was. Okay, ומשני. u'mishni. מי אמר רבי אליעזר
בעינן עד ידע אי בשרץ אטמי אי בנבלה אטמי? Mi amar Rabbi
Eliezer be'inan ad yeida ee b'sheretz itmei ee b'neveilah itmei? So he
started with putting out there exactly his understanding of Rabbi Eliezer. From
our משנה mishnah he says that it's clear that Rabbi Eliezer requires
that you start by knowing specifically how you became טמא, tamei, whether
through touching a שרץ sheretz or a נבלה neveilah or exactly how.
Now is that really true that that's a general requirement that Rabbi
Eliezer has for somebody in order to bring a חטאת chatas offering?
That they have to start with a very specific concrete knowledge of
their sin. I am going to show you, says עולא, Ulla, that
Rabbi Eliezer normally does not require that, that specific and concrete knowledge.
Okay, ורמינהו. u'reminhu. I'll ask you on this. We have a משנה.
mishnah. אמר רבי אליעזר, Amar Rabbi Eliezer, so a person basically did
this:
he had in front of him
חלב ונותר, cheilev v'nosar, right? Two things that you're forbidden to eat
and they are אסור assur and you get כרת kareis for them.
Right? The fat of an animal and נותר, nosar, a קרבן korban
that was left over. And the person ate one of those pieces,
one of those pieces of meat. Okay, and he doesn't know which
one he ate, but one way or the other way, he definitely
ate something that he's חייב כרת chayav kareis and that would obligate
him to bring a חטאת. chatas. Does such a person bring a
קרבן חטאת? korban chatas? He knows he did a sin that he's
חייב כרת chayav kareis for, he just doesn't know specifically which one.
Does he bring a קרבן חטאת? korban chatas? Is that part of
the requirement to obligate you in a חטאת chatas that you know
the concrete specifics of which exact category of sin that you have
done? So Rabbi Eliezer says you don't need to know that. אמר
רבי אליעזר מה נפשך. Amar Rabbi Eliezer mah nafshach. Which you know
whichever way you want it. מה נפשך Mah nafshach means it doesn't
matter which way it falls out. Like מה נפשך, mah nafshach, what's
your desire? Either way, whichever way it falls out, you're going to
be חייב. chayav. Okay. חלב אכל חייב נותר אכל חייב. Cheilev achal
chayav nosar achal chayav. Whichever one he ate, he's חייב. chayav. Or
let's say the question was, he did מלאכה melachah and he doesn't
realize if he did מלאכה melachah on שבת Shabbos or on יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur. Okay. So שבת חילל חייב יום כיפור חילל חייב.
Shabbos chillail chayav Yom Kippur chillail chayav. He knows he did one
of them, who cares which one, and you still, he did it
בשוגג, b'shogeg, he brings a קרבן. korban. Why does he have to
know the specifics? Are there different
מיתות? misos? יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, yeah, one is מיתת בית דין,
misas beis din, but that's only במזיד. b'meizid. Okay. Or a man
knows he slept with a woman he's not supposed to sleep with,
but he doesn't remember... try to imagine this scenario, whether it was
his wife when she was a נדה niddah or whether it was
his sister. Okay. אשתו נדה בעל חייב אחותו בעל חייב. Ishto niddah
ba'al chayav achoso ba'al chayav.
So either way, you know you did a sin that you're חייב
כרת chayav kareis for if you did it intentionally. You did it
unintentionally, you know you bring the חטאת. chatas. What difference does it
make? Bring the חטאת. chatas. Okay. אמר לו רבי יהושע. Amar lo
Rabbi Yehoshua. Rabbi יהושע Yehoshua said to him, הרי הוא אומר, harei
hu omer, the verse says, או הודע אליו חטאתו אשר חטא בה,
o hoda eilav chattaso asher chata bah, that his sin is known
through which he sinned. So אשר חטא בה, asher chata bah, you
have to know the specifics through which you sinned. עד שיודע לך
במה חטא, ad she'yivada lach bameh chata,
until it is known to you exactly how you sinned. Okay, so
that's obviously we normally assume a Rabbi יהושע Yehoshua position that a
קרבן חטאת korban chatas is much more specific, it's not generic. Okay,
but regardless, putting that aside anyway, we see Rabbi Eliezer doesn't require
even to know what type of sin you did. So in this
case, you know specifically what sin you did: you were טמא, tamei,
you entered into the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Why should he have
to require that you know the specific way you became טמא? tamei?
That seems, that does not seem at all important. So the גמרא
Gemara says,
so עולא Ulla answers,
ומשני, u'mishni, and he answers, התם אשר חטא והביא אמר רחמנא. hasam
asher chata v'heivi amar Rachmana.
Bracketing the word בה bah for a minute, which is Rabbi יהושע's
Yehoshua's דיוק, diyuk, the emphasis of the תורה Torah is that you
sinned and you bring a קרבן. korban. That the focus on the
קרבן korban is the fact that you have sinned. So that you
have... you have sinned in some way, so the specifics are not
important in a general קרבן חטאת. korban chatas.
התם אשר חטא והביא אמר
רחמנא. Hasam asher chata v'heivi amar Rachmana. כל
שהוא חטא, Kol shehu chata, however you sinned, it doesn't matter, the
focus is you did a sin, you bring a חטאת. chatas. הכא
מכדי כתיב. Hacha michdi kesiv. Here let's take a look. It says
בכל דבר טמא. b'chol davar tamei. It says if somebody touches a
טמא tamei object. As I was saying a minute ago, why did
it need to give me the specifics? I know how... people become
טמא, tamei, או בנבלת שרץ טמא למה לי, o benevelat sheretz tamei
lama li, why did it have to say or this way or
this way or this way, who cares? שמע מינה בינה עד יד
דאי בשרץ יתני ואי בנבילה יתני, shema mina beina ad yad dei
besheretz itnei ve'i beneveila itnei, the fact that the תורה Torah is
being very specific and concrete here and it's completely superfluous tells you
you need to know exactly how you become טמא. tamei. Now that
explains why there's a difference based on the פסוקים, pesukim, it doesn't
explain the logic of the difference, right? I mean, again, I think
what you see is what we've been seeing from the beginning is
the high degree of specificity that the תורה Torah has, certainly through
the גמרא's Gemara lens,
of dealing with the sins of טומאת מקדש. tumat mikdash. You know,
this קרבן korban on יום כיפור Yom Kippur does this part of
it, this קרבן korban on יום כיפור Yom Kippur does this, this
for ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, this for ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, right,
all these different things to deal with טומאת מקדש. tumat mikdash. So
here too, like it's not just some type of generic thing is
not enough. We don't deal with generics here. We deal with specifics.
Maybe it's sort of like the פסוק pasuk we quoted at the
end of the day
yesterday, להבדיל בין הקודש ובין החול ובין הטמא ובין הטהור, lehavdil bein
hakodesh uvein hachol uvein hatamei uvein hatahor, like you know, the whole
idea of טומאת מקדש tumat mikdash is that it requires a high
degree of, you know, vigilance and discernment and so on, so maybe
that's why we're being so specific. But anyway, he's not interested in
that. He's not writing טעמי המצוות, ta'amei hamitzvot, he's just telling you
legally it's based on the fact that the פסוק pasuk was very
specific here. What you see is that he explains that רבי אליעזר's
Rabbi Eliezer debate with רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is that רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer requires the specific knowledge of how you became טמא. tamei.
Yeah, first Shmuel and then... So I know I touched a dead
animal carcass, I just don't know whether it qualifies as a שרץ
sheretz or not. That's a different discussion earlier in the גמרא Gemara
that deals with ידיעת בית רבה yedi'at beit rabba and so on.
Right, so that was like a different discussion. Yeah, it's a difference
of יום כיפור Yom Kippur is going to atone or cleanse all
of the
טומאות, tumot, right? So you know that there's a... Yeah, but not
this one because this... that's an interesting question. Like if this one
doesn't fall within the specifics here, does it get caught in יום
כיפור? Yom Kippur? Because יום כיפור Yom Kippur is only ידיעה בתחילה
ולא ידיעה בסוף, yedi'a batchila ve'lo yedi'a basof, whatever...
it's like this case where it actually was exactly the right parameters
of like ידיעה בתחילה, yedi'a batchila, העלם בינתיים, hellem beintayim, ידיעה בסוף,
yedi'a basof, but it was some technical problem, right? So that's unclear.
That's similar to, you know, רבנו תם's Rabbeinu Tam point about what
do you do for רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer if somebody didn't know it was a בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
and they knew they were טמא. tamei. Right, so there also it
isn't being covered by any of the things. So where's that covered?
You know, so there's like no specific answer to that. That's why
רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam says maybe you bring a normal חטאת chatat
in that case. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this:
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, now רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would answer back
because רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says you don't need to know the
specifics. So top of י"ט עמוד א'. yud tet amud alef. איידי
דבעי למכתב בהמה וחיה, aidi deba'ei lemichtav behema vechaya,
since it had to say or you touch like a dead בהמה
behema or a dead חיה, chaya, whatever, and the reason for that
we discussed in an earlier גמרא, Gemara, I don't want to go
over that again. Anyway, because there is something we learn out from
some of the concrete specifics of the פסוקים, pesukim,
כדרבי, kichde rebbi, to teach me the teaching of רבי, Rebbi, which
we dealt with about twelve דפים dapim ago, כתיב נמי שרץ. ketiv
nami sheretz. We also teach שרץ, sheretz, כדתני דבי רבי ישמעאל כל
פרשה שנאמרה ונשנית לא נשנית אלא בשביל דבר שנתחדש בה. ki d'tani
d'vei Rabbi Yishmael kol parsha shene'emra venishn'it lo nishn'it ela bishvil davar
shenitchadesh bah. If something is repeated, it could be that the whole
thing is repeated just to tell you one new הלכה. halacha. Okay,
so here too, he basically says, fine, it didn't have to give
you all the specifics, but some of the specifics were teaching you
something and that's why it gave it to them. So that's the
debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, whether you need to know the specific thing
in which you became טמא. tamei. But both of them agree you
only bring this קרבן korban if you forgot that you were טמא.
tamei. If you forgot that it was מקדש, Mikdash, you would not
bring a קרבן korban according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי
אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. And רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, who's the author of
the idea of שתים שהן ארבע, shetayim shehen arba, says you would
bring a קרבן korban whether what you forgot was the טומאה, tumah,
whether what you forgot was the מקדש Mikdash and the קרבנות. korbanot.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this: רבי אליעזר האי בה
מאי עביד ליה? Rabbi Eliezer hai bah mai avid lei? Now since,
now going back to the debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua about you don't know if you ate חלב
chelev or you ate דם, dam, right, so רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
says what we always assume, that you need to know the specific
sin that you did, that's the אשר חטא בה, asher chata bah,
that you sinned therein, like with that specific sin. So רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer, who does not use the word בה bah to tell
you that, he says it's enough that you sinned, okay, what does
he do with the word בה? bah? רבי אליעזר האי בה מאי
עביד ליה? Rabbi Eliezer hai bah mai avid lei? פרט למתעסק, perat
lemit'asek,
to exclude the case when you are doing something just, like, completely
incidentally. Okay, now what does that mean? So a classic example is...
like this is always an interesting line of where's the difference between
שוגג shogeg and מתעסק. mit'asek. שוגג shogeg is you sort of know
very specifically what you are doing, but you are unaware of important
facts. You're unaware that the act is forbidden. You're unaware that the
thing that you're eating is חלב. chelev. You're unaware that you are
טמא. tamei. You're unaware that you are entering into the בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash. That's שוגג. shogeg. You know the physical action you're doing,
but you're unaware of relevant facts that tell you that it would
be a sin, and otherwise you wouldn't be doing it. That's when
you bring a קרבן. korban. What's מתעסק mit'asek when you don't bring
a קרבן? korban? So a classic example is... What example of מתעסק,
misasek, the example I like giving in general of מתעסק misasek is
that you're just like walking somewhere and accidentally you bump into a
light switch and you turn on the light. Okay, so there was
like the action that you did was completely incidental to the act
that you were trying to do, and there wasn't even an awareness
that that might have happened. It was like a slip, okay? That's
different than אינו מתכוין. eino miskavein. A classic case in the גמרא
Gemara of אינו מתכוין eino miskavein is that you're let's say dragging
a chair across a garden and it's making a furrow, and you
weren't intending for it to make a furrow. And it might not
even definitely have made a furrow. There's a debate: are you allowed
to do it if it will possibly make and possibly no, not
make? But at least in that case, you know, if you had
been paying attention, you would have been aware that the chair could
have possibly been making a furrow. That's like an אינו מתכוין. eino
miskavein. מתעסק misasek is like completely different. מתעסק misasek is almost like
you're oblivious to the possibility and it just happened in passing. Another
good example about מתעסק misasek is you're walking down the street and
all of a sudden, I mean, it's pretty similar to my light
switch example, you're walking down the street and all of a sudden
the street lamps go on because they were electric eye and you
didn't realize that they were electric eye. Now, if you realize that
there's an electric eye in the street and you're still walking down,
then that's possibly different. Anyway, רש״י Rashi's example of מתעסק misasek
or a גמרא Gemara's example of מתעסק misasek is let's say I'm
trying to, there's different degrees, but let's say I'm trying to pick
this apple, I see a tomato on the ground and I think
that it's no longer growing and I'm just trying to pick it
up off the ground, and I didn't realize that it was still
attached to the vine. And as I'm picking it up off the
ground, I pluck it off of the vine. Okay? So there, it's
like, you know, there it's שבת, Shabbos, so I have obviously done
a מלאכה, melacha, okay? So there it's like, you know, there some
of these things get to be a little bit of a question.
Is it שוגג? shogeg? You could say, I did the physical act
I wanted to do, I picked the tomato off the ground, so
maybe it's a שוגג. shogeg. I didn't realize that by picking it
I would be plucking a tomato off of a vine. Or you
could say no, that's מתעסק misasek because the act I wanted to
do was an act of picking something off the ground, not an
act of plucking something off a vine, right?
So that's like an issue that's an interesting like debate: you call
that מתעסק. misasek. A more obvious case is, there actually is a
tomato that's off the vine on the ground, I bend down to
pick it, but I'm so involved in my conversation with כנען, Canaan,
then accidentally my hand goes to the tomato next to it which
is attached to the vine and I pick that tomato off. That's
a case where I like slip and do something, the actual act
I do is a physically different act than the one I wanted
to do. Okay, all of those are cases of מתעסק. misasek. So
the point is by מתעסק, misasek, the basic rule is, is that
it's not the act is not associated with you. By a שוגג,
shogeg, it's your action, you just were not fully aware of the
fact that it was a violation because you weren't aware of certain
facts or certain laws. You were violating and you were unwittingly violating,
but still it's your act that you've done, but you're unwittingly doing
a violation. Here, to some degree, because your physical action was different
than the one you intended it to be, okay, it's not even
associated with you, it's not even considered like it's your action at
all, and you don't have to bring a קרבן. korban. So that's
the idea. בפרט ליה מתעסק Baprat lei misasek says אשר חטא בה.
asher chata bah. You have to like be doing the thing that
you're doing. Okay, and then because you're unaware, you're not מזיד, meizid,
you bring a קרבן. korban. But if somehow some other thing you
were doing that you weren't intending to do you did, then you
don't even have to bring a קרבן, korban, then like you're totally
off the hook. And what was the אינו מתכוין? eino miskavein? אינו
מתכוין eino miskavein is a case where you're aware that something might
result from your action but you're not intending it, or maybe you're
not consciously aware, but if I were to stop and tell you,
you know, "Hey, you know, David, what do you think's going to
happen as you're, if you're drawing that chair, you're dragging that chair
across the garden? Do you think something could happen?" You say, "Yeah,
well, it's possible I guess that a furrow could be made or
whatever."
Right. You don't bring a קרבן? korban? No, by אינו... well, אינו
מתכוין eino miskavein is debated. We basically rule that אינו מתכוין eino
miskavein, you're allowed to do if you, what do you call it,
if it's not definitely going to result from it. According to the
opinion that says that you're not allowed to do an אינו מתכוין,
eino mitkavein, if you,
I have to remind myself, I think he says that it's אסור
assur to do, but whether he would say that if when you
dragged the chair the furrow did get made would that mean that
you're חייב chayav a קרבן, korban, I'm not remembering if according to
that opinion you're חייב chayav a קרבן korban or not. But we
definitely, anyway, but there's an opinion that says you're certainly
not
allowed to do it
לכתחילה. lechatchila. לכתחילה Lechatchila you mean if you realize that this might
cause the furrow? But if it won't definitely cause it, but you
realize it might, so we actually are ruled that you're allowed to
do it. Okay, but there's an opinion that you're not allowed, but
even the opinion that you're not allowed, if it winds up causing
the furrow, I'm pretty sure he would not say you bring a
קרבן. korban. But anyway, but we rule you are allowed to do
it unless it will definitely result from the act. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. But we rule that unless it
definitely will result from it, you're allowed to do it. Okay, that
has to do with the whole question of are you allowed to
use the hot water, the water, hot water in your building on
שבת Shabbos if you live in a apartment building. Because the reason
you're not, the problem of using the hot water in your building
is you're not heating up that water, that water is already heated.
The point is that it takes water out of the hot water
heater and it brings in cold water. And depending on the various
circumstances, the bringing in of that cold water might get if the
other remaining water is hot enough, the bringing in of that cold
water will cook the cold water that's coming in, or it might
also trigger the fire to go on because of the change of
temperature. So the question is okay, maybe it will, maybe it won't.
You don't know which it will do. So therefore, it all depends
on the current state of the hot water heater. So some people
want to say oh, אינו מתכוין, eino mitkavein? so it's מותר. mutar.
It won't definitely happen. Others say, and I'm totally digressing, but I'll
just say, others say no, there it either definitely will happen or
definitely won't happen. You just don't know the specifics of the circumstances
right now. If you were to go to the superintendent and go
into the basement and get a reading of that thing, you would
know a hundred percent, either it a hundred percent will happen or
a hundred percent won't happen. So there, it's like the all the
information is there about whether it will or won't happen. You're just
ignorant of that information. So is that considered אינו מתכוין? All right.
Anyway, yeah. If you definitely don't make a furrow, you should certainly
be פטור. pator. No, so you definitely don't make a furrow and
you would do it, then that would be an interesting question about
whether you would even be considered to be a מתעסק misyasek or
like what. I mean, you wouldn't be חייב. chayav. No, maybe not
because it's probably מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה, melacha she'eina tzricha l'gufa, but
it's complicated. Anyway, yeah. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Okay, but anyways that's anyway. So I so that was
that two words מתעסק, misyasek, but תוספות Tosafot gets, you know, uses
the opportunity to discuss מתעסק, misyasek, so I decided I would as
well. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: רבי יוחנן אמר
משמוש דורשין איכא בינייהו. Rabbi Yochanan amar mishmosh dorshin ika beinaihu. Back
to the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי אליעזר. Rabbi
Eliezer. What difference does it make whether you say that you have
to have העלם טומאה helem tumah or העלם שרץ? helem sheretz? Okay,
so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says no, they're really not debating. They
both agree, even רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer isn't saying you have to
completely know how you became טמא. tamei. So they're really saying the
exact same thing. You're only חייב chayav if you don't know you
were טמא, tamei, you're not חייב chayav a קרבן korban if you
don't know you entered into the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So why
does one frame it one way and one frame it the other
way? So it's משמוש דורשין, mishmosh dorshin, which just means they're just
disagreeing which part of the פסוק pasuk you get it from. They're
not disagreeing with the הלכה. halacha.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva learned it from the פסוק pasuk where it
says והוא טמא ונעלם ממנו. v'hu tamei v'ne'elam mimenu.
He focuses on the word טמא. tamei. And רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
focuses on the word שרץ, sheretz, but they both really exact agree
to the הלכה. halacha. משמוש דורשין איכא בינייהו. mishmosh dorshin ika beinaihu.
ואיתימא רב ששת משמוש דורשין איכא בינייהו. v'iseima Rav Sheshet mishmosh dorshin
ika beinaihu.
דרב ששת מחליף, d'Rav Sheshet machlif, because רב ששת Rav Sheshet sometimes
when he would tell over this משנה, Mishna, he would sometimes like
just reverse who said which, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, because it doesn't really matter. They're both saying the exact
same thing. מחליף רבי אליעזר לרבי עקיבא ורבי עקיבא לרבי אליעזר, machlif
Rabbi Eliezer l'Rabbi Akiva v'Rabbi Akiva l'Rabbi Eliezer, just to show, you
know, maybe he did it intentionally to show that they're not really
disagreeing, or maybe he didn't even bother like figuring out who said
what because they're saying the exact same point. They're just learning out
from different words in the פסוקים. pesukim. Okay. Now, בעי מיניה רבא
מרב נחמן. ba'ei minei Rava meiRav Nachman. רבא Rava asked רב נחמן
Rav Nachman the following question: according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, you're only bringing a קרבן korban if you
forgot you were טמא, tamei, not if you forgot the מקדש. Mikdash.
העלם זה וזה בידו מהו? Helem zeh v'zeh b'yado mahu? Let's say
you forgot both. You forgot you were טמא tamei and you forgot
that this was a מקדש. Mikdash. So do we say, you mean
you still transgressed the part you're חייב chayav for? Well, that's the
question. Do we say that oh, that the specifics, once they're being
so arbitrary, I mean, so you know, they're saying it's not enough
that you're sinning in ignorance, you have to be a specific type
of an ignorance, right? So if you're distinguishing between טומאה tumah that
you're not knowing you're טמא tamei and not knowing that this is
a מקדש, Mikdash, so do we say that as soon that it's
only not knowing you're טמא tamei and at the same time being
aware that this is a מקדש? Mikdash? Or do we say, you
know, that not knowing you're טמא tamei is the sufficient cause, it's
not that it's specifically that configuration? Okay. So what do we say?
אמר ליה הרי העלם טומאה בידו וחייב. amar lei harei helem tumah
b'yado v'chayav. So his first answer is Michael's answer. Okay, you have
all that they required was that you not know you're טמא. tamei.
They didn't say they required that you're aware that it be a
מקדש, Mikdash, right? They just said being ignorant of a מקדש Mikdash
is not sufficient or doesn't is not relevant. But as long as
you're not aware you're טמא, tamei, that's the requirement and you bring
a
קרבן. korban. הרי העלם טומאה בידו וחייב. harei helem tumah b'yado v'chayav.
Some say אדרבא הרי העלם מקדש בידו ופטור. aderaba harei helem Mikdash
b'yado v'pator. I'll say the opposite. Maybe they're saying if you don't
know that it's the מקדש, Mikdash, that is that's sufficient to say
you don't bring a קרבן. korban. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי, amar lei
Ravina l'Rav Ashi, so רבינא Ravina said to רב אשי, Rav Ashi,
I skipped a line. אמר רב אשי חזינן. amar Rav Ashi chazinan.
Let's assess the situation. אי מטומאה קא פריש
הרי העלם טומאה בידו וחייב
אי ממקדש קא פריש הרי העלם מקדש בידו ופטור. ei mi'tumah ka
parish harei helem tumah b'yado v'chayav ei mi'mikdash ka parish harei
helem Mikdash b'yado v'pator. He says, let's ask the guy. Let's say
to him, hey Michael. Now of course there's an interesting question how
to read this, but I'll give the first version. Hey Michael. If
somebody told you, right, so you were completely ignorant that you were
both and you went ahead and you ate this קרבן, korban, and
I say, Michael, think back into your state of mind an hour
ago before you ate it, if somebody had told you you were
טמא, tamei, would you have realized, "Oh my God, I'm טמא, tamei,
that means that... oh right, right, and this is a קרבן, korban,
I better not eat it." Okay, would that have been enough to
trigger for you all the awareness to make you aware and you
would therefore not have eaten? If so, then the key thing that
you forgot was the fact you were טמא tamei because had you
remembered that, it would have triggered your memory of the other thing.
You sort of get that, right? If you're aware you're טמא, tamei,
then you sort of think about the implications of that and that
would have triggered your memories. Now, let's say I say to you,
"Hey, Michael, if somebody were to say to you, 'Hey, that's a
קרבן,' korban, would that have triggered your memory that you're טמא?" tamei?
So he says if A would have triggered your memory or B,
then it shows that A is the key thing you forgot. If
B would have triggered your memory of A, it shows B is
the key thing that you forgot. Now, the responses to that could
be: One minute, first of all, there could be a scenario where
neither would have triggered either memory, and there could be a scenario
where A would have triggered B and B would have triggered A,
especially it depends the context in which I said that to Michael.
I said, "Michael, what are you doing? You're טמא!" tamei! He says,
"Who cares? Oh, this must be a קרבן!" korban! Right? A little
bit might depend on the way in which I'm alerting you to
the fact that you're טמא. tamei. So anyway, but let's say A
would have triggered B and B would have triggered A, it still
doesn't get to decide which is the fundamental one, okay? But anyway,
but maybe רב אשי Rav Ashi is saying is, in a case
where one would have triggered the other and not the reverse, then
the one that would have triggered the other is the primary thing
you forgot and that's the one in which we say will determine
whether or not you bring the קרבן korban or not. So let's
read that again. אמר רב אשי חזינא, Amar Rav Ashi chazina, we
take a look. אי מטומאה קא פריש, I mi'tuma ka parish, if
saying that you're טמא tamei would have made you separate
because it would have made you remember that it's a קרבן, korban,
so הרי העלם טומאה בידו, harei he'elam tuma beyado, fundamentally what we're
dealing with here is forgetting that you're טמא, tamei, וחייב ve'chayav and
you're חייב. chayav. אם ממקדש קא פריש, Im mi'mikdash ka parish, if
telling you that this was the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash or קרבן
korban would have been enough to make you separate, הרי העלם מקדש
בידו, harei he'elam mikdash beyado, the fundamental thing you forgot was that
it was a בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, ופטור u'pattur and then you'd
be פטור. pattur. אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי, Amar lei Ravina le'Rav
Ashi, so רבינא Ravina said that to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, one
minute, at the end of the day the reality, who cares what
would have triggered what? He forgot both, right? כלום פריש מטומאה אלא
משום מקדש? Kelum parish mi'tuma ella mishum mikdash? The only reason he
separated from the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash was because he also realized
that he was טמא. tamei. כלום פריש ממקדש אלא משום טומאה? Kelum
parish mi'mikdash ella mishum tuma? And the only reason he separated from
the טומאה tuma was because he realized he was about to enter
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Meaning, who cares? At the end of
the day, who cares what would have triggered what? This still is
the reality that you forgot both, and therefore you haven't really answered
the question: what's the story if you forgot both? אלא, Ella, he
says, לא שנא. lo shna. It doesn't matter which would have triggered
what. Okay, לא שנא, lo shna, fine, but what's the הלכה? halacha?
So you forgot both. Do you bring a קרבן korban or not?
So רש"י, Rashi, and I have no idea how רש"י Rashi knows
this, is רש"י Rashi says, אלא לא שנא, ella lo shna, if
you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says, where's רש"י? Rashi? But
six lines before the lines get wide: ופטור. u'pattur. So רש"י Rashi
decides the conclusion of the גמרא Gemara is פטור. pattur. Oh, that's
interesting. I would have thought the opposite too. Okay, but anyway, רש"י
Rashi assumes that no, you know, anyway, that's a fascinating question. I
think we all would have agreed that the פשט pshat would have
been once you forgot טומאה, tuma, that's suffice to bring the חיוב
chiyuv of bringing a קרבן. korban. But the גמרא Gemara suggests maybe
you need the specific configuration of forgetting your טומאה tuma and knowing
the other thing, or at least in רב אשי's Rav Ashi version
that the forgetting of the טומאה tuma is the primary. Okay. Well,
this is according to the opinions that say you have to know
also if it's נבילה neveilah or שרץ sheretz or whatever? No, even
with רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. No. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. שני שבילין אחד טמא ואחד
טהור. Shnei shvilin echad tamei ve'echad tahor. Now we're going to continue
with this question of what does it mean to be aware or
to not aware or to whatever. Okay, so there are two paths.
You know that there is a dead body buried under one of
them and therefore if you go on the one that is טמא,
tamei, you know you will become טמא. tamei. There's no way to
walk down that one without being טמא. tamei. But you don't know
which one you walked on, or you don't know which path is
which. Okay. So you walked on one. הלך בראשונה ולא נכנס, Halach
b'rishonah ve'lo nichnas, and you didn't go into the בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash. Okay. בשניה ונכנס, Bishniyah ve'nichnas, and then you went in the
second one and you went into the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. And
then when you went in, then you forgot that you had walked
on both of the paths, okay, or one of them. We'll see.
Anyway, so you definitely became טמא. tamei. You don't know which path
made you טמא, tamei, but you definitely became טמא. tamei. You forgot
about it. You entered the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So the הלכה
halacha is חייב, chayav, you're חייב. chayav. Now, it would be an
interesting question what would רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer say? Would this be
like not knowing the נבילה, neveilah, not knowing the שרץ, sheretz, or
since you definitely knew you became טמא tamei through a מת, meis,
you just don't know whether it was on Monday when I walked
on path A or on Tuesday when I walked on path B.
Okay, anyway, it's not clear whether רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would debate
this, but anyway, you definitely know you're טמא, tamei, you forgot about
it, everybody agrees you're חייב. chayav. At least everybody we're discussing. הלך
בראשונה ונכנס. Halach b'rishonah ve'nichnas. Now let's say you went on path
A and you went into the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. You forgot
you did it and you went into the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
At that moment, you were a ספק safek violator בשוגג. beshogeig. You
weren't aware, you had forgotten that you had done it. Okay. הזה
ושנה וטבל. Hizah ve'shanah ve'taval. Then you went to have the sprinkling.
the ashes of the פרה אדומה parah adumah once and twice, you
went into the מקוה. mikvah. Now you're טהור tahor because you had
remembered that you had walked on path A. So you got rid
of that ספק טומאה. safeik tumah. ואחר הלך בשניה ונכנס. Veachar halach
bashniya venichnas. Then you walked on path B and you forgot about
it and you entered into בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash so now you
did another שוגג shogeg being in a state of ספק. safeik.
Okay,
now in this case either on Monday when you went into the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash after having gone on path A, or on
Tuesday when you went into the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash after having
gone on path B, on one of those days you violated. So
you definitely violated. At the moment you violated you were unaware that
you were טמא, tamei, but you don't know which day it was
that you violated. Okay, is that sufficient to say I'm bringing a
קרבן korban either for Monday or for Tuesday? It's not exactly like
the חלב cheilev or the נבילה. neveilah. You know specifically that you
have done a sin of entering into the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
בטומאה. betumah. Okay, you just don't know which day it was that
you, which act it was that was that sin. Okay, so would
that be sufficient? רבי שמעון פוטר. Rabbi Shimon poter. רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon exempts you in this case from a קרבן. korban. ורבי שמעון
בן יהודה פוטר מכולן משום רבי שמעון. Verabbi Shimon ben Yehuda poter
mikulam mishum Rabbi Shimon. רבי שמעון בן יהודה Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda
in the name of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said that you're פטור
patur even in the first case. And the first case, remember, you
just went on path A and then path B and then into
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you're definitely טמא. tamei. So that's a
little bizarre why he should be פטור patur in the first case.
So now we're going to... ובכולן Uvechulan says the גמרא, Gemara, in
all of them? ואפילו בקמייתא, Veafillu bekamaisa, even in the first one?
ממה נפשך, Mimma nafshach, make up your mind. טמא
הוא, Tamei hu, you're טמא. tamei. You went on path A, then
you went on path B, then you went into the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha bemai
askinan, כגון שהלך בראשונה. kegon shehalach berishona. You went on path A.
ובשעה שהלך בשניה שכח שהלך בראשונה. Ubeshaah shehalach bashniya shachach shehalach berishona.
Then you went on path B and you forgot that you had
gone on path A and then you forgot having gone on path
B. Okay, meaning at no point were you aware that you were
definitely טמא. tamei. Okay, I went on path A on Monday, I
went on path B on Tuesday, and I went into the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash on Wednesday. On Wednesday there was I was 100%
טמא tamei no question. But at no point was I ever aware
that I was ודאי טמא. vaday tamei. When after having gone on
path A, I was aware I was ספק טמא. safeik tamei. Then
I forgot I was on path A. I went on path B
so I was aware I was ספק טמא safeik tamei because I
remembered that I had gone on path B, but I had not
remembered path A. So I only remembered at any given time that
I was ספק טמא. safeik tamei. Then I forgot that and then
I went in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay, so you were
aware that you were ספק טמא safeik tamei but you actually were
ודאי טמא. vaday tamei. Is that considered enough of an awareness to
say you knew and then you
forgot? Okay. הכא במאי עסקינן כגון שהלך בראשונה ובשעה שהלך בשניה שכח
שהלך בראשונה Hacha bemai askinan kegon shehalach berishona ubeshaah shehalach bashniya shachach
shehalach berishona דהוי ליה מקצת ידיעה. dehavi lei miktzas yediyah. You have
a partial awareness of being definitely טמא. tamei. You are definitely
טמא. tamei. ובהא קמיפלגי. Uveha kamiflegi. This is the debate. תנא קמא
סבר אמרינן מקצת ידיעה ככל ידיעה. Tanna Kamma savar amrinan miktzas yediyah
kechol yediyah. That's fine. As long as you were definitely טמא tamei
and you were somewhat aware of that fact, okay, then it's knowledge
and therefore you bring a קרבן. korban. ורבי שמעון סבר, Verabbi Shimon
savar, and the final רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon holds, לא אמרינן מקצת
ידיעה ככל ידיעה. lo amrinan miktzas yediyah kechol yediyah. No, that doesn't
count. Okay, so that's the last opinion. The last opinion says that
even if you were ודאי טמא, vaday tamei, if you weren't aware
you were ודאי טמא, vaday tamei, you're not חייב chayav a
קרבן. korban. Okay, now, now הלך בראשונה. halach berishona. Now going back
to that was the, that was the more extreme case that, you
know, you went on both paths and even so somebody would say
you're exempt
because even though you were ודאי טמא vaday tamei you weren't aware
you were ודאי טמא, vaday tamei, you're only aware you're ספק טמא.
safeik tamei. Now how about the earlier debate about going on path
A and forgetting going to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, going on
path B forgetting and going to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash where
you one of those days you sinned but we don't even know
which day you sinned. Okay, so in that case is that sufficient
to bring a קרבן? korban? So let's go back to that. הלך
בראשונה ונכנס הזה ושנה וטבל וחזר והלך בשניה ונכנס חייב. Halach berishona
venichnas hiza veshana vetaval vechazar vehalach bashniya venichnas chayav. So the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma says in that case you are חייב chayav at
the end of the day. Okay, you were aware and you forgot
although it was only aware and forgot of ספק, safeik, but if
you combine the two cases in one of them you actually did
the sin. Okay, so even, so even though at no point were
you ודאי טמא, vaday tamei, that doesn't matter. We can combine the
two and say in one of those cases you have to bring
a קרבן. korban. Okay, so רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon,
so the גמרא Gemara says ורבי שמעון פוטר. Verabbi Shimon poter. ואמאי
חייב? Veamai chayav? ספק ידיעה הוא? Safeik yediyah hu? Why are you
חייב chayav according to the first opinion? Okay, according to the first
case, you know, any particular day you were not definitely טמא, tamei,
so that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying is that should not
be a sufficient state of like, oh, you were aware you were
טמא, tamei, right? It's one thing to say you were somewhat aware,
the reality was you were ודאי טמא vaday tamei and you were
somewhat aware, that's one thing. But in these cases on any given
day you were ספק טמא. safeik tamei. Why is that enough of
a knowledge and an awareness to be מחייב mechayev you a
קרבן? korban? So אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, כאן עשו ספק
ידיעה כידיעה. kan asu safeik yediyah kiyediyah. Yeah, you're right, here it's
true. The whole thing was only a ספק safek at the time,
but that's enough. Now he doesn't say why it's enough, כאן עשו,
kan asu, like here's an exception. We'll see when we get to
the bottom of the דף daf why this is an exception. Says
yeah, I understand the problem. Here, even when you were sinning, you
weren't definitely sinning. It's only when you combine Monday and Tuesday. Okay,
but nevertheless, that's enough here. ריש לקיש אמר Reish Lakish amar no,
הא מני רבי ישמעאל היא דאמר לא בעינן ידיעה בתחילה. ha mani
Rabbi Yishmael hi d'amar lo beinan yedia bet'chila. No, this doesn't count
as being aware. Being aware, when even had you known everything, you
only would have known that it was a ספק, safek, that's not
being aware. This is רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
doesn't require that you be aware at the beginning. For רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael you could have been ignorant all along, and then at
the end when you become aware, you're חייב. chayav. So here it
doesn't matter what state of awareness you had. At the end you
were aware, oh, Monday or Tuesday I went into the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash I was טמא. tamei. That's enough to bring a קרבן.
korban. Now where does רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael say that? Interestingly, רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael doesn't explicitly say that. But since the פסוק pasuk
says to remind you, the פסוק pasuk says the word ונעלם v'ne'elam
twice. ונעלם ממנו והוא טמא ואשם, v'ne'elam mimenu v'hu tamei v'ashem, whatever,
ונעלם ממנו. v'ne'elam mimenu. It says ונעלם ונעלם. v'ne'elam v'ne'elam. So what
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva does is, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says the
first והוא טמא, v'hu tamei, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says the first
ונעלם v'ne'elam tells you only העלם טומאה, he'elam tumah, okay, you're not
חייב chayav if it's העלם מקדש. he'elam mikdash. And the second one
tells you, the second והעלם v'he'elam tells you
that you need ידיעה בתחילה. yedia bet'chila. Okay, it's not enough to
be completely ignorant from beginning to self, you have to first know
and then forget. That's what the two ונעלם v'ne'elam tells you. רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says
ונעלם v'ne'elam is העלם טומאה he'elam tumah and the second ונעלם v'ne'elam
is העלם
מקדש, he'elam mikdash, okay, or קודש kodesh or whatever, קרבן. korban. Okay,
and that's when you get the two that are four. You either
forget טומאה tumah or forget מקדש. mikdash. But for him there's no
extra ונעלם. v'ne'elam. So for him you could have been ignorant from
the very beginning. You didn't need to be aware and then forget.
So from that, from the implication, because רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael never
explicitly says it, the גמרא Gemara assumes that for רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael you never had to be aware from the beginning. Okay, so
now we're going to look at this issue about why this case
would be different than even if you did require awareness, why according
to at least one version, ספק ידיעה safek yedia for רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan suffices. Even though you were never really, you were never
definitely טמא, tamei, that doesn't matter. You could never have been aware
that you were definitely טמא, tamei, it doesn't matter. So let's take
a look. ורמי רבי יוחנן אדרבי יוחנן. v'rami Rabbi Yochanan a'Rabbi Yochanan.
So we're going to show a contradiction of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
against himself. ורמי ריש לקיש אדריש לקיש. v'rami Reish Lakish a'Reish Lakish.
And ריש לקיש Reish Lakish against himself. How they read this case
as opposed to how they read another case. דתניא, de'tanya, אחת ספק
חלב ונודע, achat safek cheilev v'noda, ספק חלב ונודע. safek cheilev v'noda.
This sounds almost exactly the same. I ate a piece of meat
that was possibly חלב, cheilev, and then I became aware. Oh my
God, I just accidentally did a sin that obligates me in a
קרבן חטאת. korban chatat. And then tomorrow, I ate another piece of
meat that was ספק חלב safek cheilev and I became aware. Okay,
now somehow the combination of the two is that I definitely ate
חלב. cheilev. So the case would be the following, okay.
One of these things is חלב, cheilev, all right?
And I go ahead and I ate and we don't know which
is which. And I ate one of them, and then I became
aware afterwards. Oh my God, one of those was חלב, cheilev, oh
my God, I might have just eaten חלב. cheilev. Okay, now I
don't bring a קרבן חטאת korban chatat because I didn't definitely sin.
Actually what I would bring at this stage would be an אשם
תלוי. asham talui. Okay, but then comes tomorrow and I'm totally, I'm
completely oblivious and I've totally forgotten about that there were two pieces
of meat and I say, "Oh look, a yummy piece of meat
here that my wife left on the table. I'm going to eat
this," and I eat this. And then somebody says, "You idiot, that
was the other piece of the thing you ate yesterday!" So says,
"Oh my God!" So now, definitely either yesterday or today I ate
חלב. cheilev. Okay, but at no stage do I know like which
piece of meat it was, right? Okay, so let's take a look.
Now, I would, so let's take a look. So, אחת ספק חלב
ונודע, achat safek cheilev v'noda, then you become aware. ספק חלב ונודע.
safek cheilev v'noda. רבי אומר, Rabbi omer, כשם שמביא חטאת על כל
אחת ואחת, keshem she'mevi chatat al kol achat v'achat, כך מביא אשם
תלוי על כל אחת ואחת. kach mevi asham talui al kol achat
v'achat. The same way, if, meaning the point is you don't bring
a חטאת chatat for both of them, but the same way, had
they both been חלב, cheilev, you would have brought a, you would
have brought a חטאת chatat for each separate piece, so you bring
an אשם תלוי asham talui for each separate piece. Now you can
hear the counterarguments, because you only did one thing wrong. You did
two acts that were ספק איסור, safek issur, but there was only
one איסור issur to be done. But רבי Rabbi says
it doesn't matter, okay? You did one act of doing a ספק
איסור, safek issur, one אשם תלוי. asham talui. Another act, another אשם
תלוי. asham talui. Even though there's only one piece of חלב cheilev
between them. That's what רבי Rabbi says, okay. ורבי שמעון בן יהודה
ורבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון אמרו משום רבי שמעון, v'Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda
v'Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon amru mishum Rabbi Shimon, אינו מביא אלא אשם
תלוי אחד. eino mevi ela asham talui echad. No, you only bring
one אשם תלוי. asham talui. שנאמר, shene'emar, על שגגתו אשר שגג. al
shigagato asher shagag. התורה ריבתה שגגות הרבה ואשם תלוי אחד. HaTorah ribeta
shegagotos harbei v'asham talui echad. It says on the errors that you
did, the Torah says that there are many שגגות, shegagotos, many types
of mistakes you could do. and only bring one אשם תלוי. asham
talui. Now it actually seems that they're saying even a more radical
thing. The case I gave you was an easier case. It seems
like they're saying like it could have been ten different scenarios with
ten different, you know, mix-ups of pieces of meat. Right, one day
Michael had two pieces of meat in his house, one was חלב,
chelev, the next חנן Chanan at his house, another at his house.
Anyway, they say it doesn't matter. The idea that you bring a
separate קרבן korban for every sin is only for when you definitely
sinned. An אשם תלוי, asham talui, which is a doubtful sin, presumably
they all have to be the same, איסור חלב, issur chelev, not
different איסורים. issurin. But if they're all the same genre of sin,
one אשם תלוי asham talui suffices for all of your various doubtful
sins that you've done within that genre. That seems to be what
they're saying. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara does here. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: ואמר ריש
לקיש כאן שנה רבי ידיעות ספקות מתחלקות
לחטאות. ve'amar Reish Lakish kan shanah Rebbi yedi'ot sfekot mit-chal-kot lechata'ot. That
doubtful awarenesses divide for different sin offerings. Meaning, the way he's understanding
רבי Rebbi is the following, okay, is that
let's take the following scenario, right? Let's say here's a piece of
definite חלב chelev and another piece of definite חלב chelev and this
guy is going ahead, I don't know who that is, I just,
no, I wanted to draw a big house and I drew a
big nose. Anyway, whatever. This is the guy. Anyway, he's going ahead
and he's eating them, okay? And he eats both pieces. How many
קרבנות korbanot does he bring? So that's the classic example of eating
two pieces of חלב chelev בהעלם אחד. be-he'elam echad. If it's in
one state of not being aware of what he's doing, he brings
one קרבן. korban. If he's aware in the middle, I guess I'll
draw a lightbulb... does that look like a lightbulb? Anyway, I don't
know what it looks like, clown on the male. Okay, he becomes
aware in the middle that he's doing an איסור issur and then
he forgets again, he brings two קרבנות. korbanot. Okay. Now what if,
okay, right. What if, okay,
that's a case. What if he became aware not that he definitely
ate חלב, chelev, but somehow in the middle he realizes, 'Oh my
god, I might have eaten חלב.' chelev. He did eat חלב, chelev,
but he maybe thought, 'I might have.' Would that be enough? Or
let's take a better case. Let's say that this was ספק חלב,
sofek chelev, this was ספק חלב, sofek chelev, in the middle he
becomes aware, 'Oh my god, I just ate ספק חלב,' sofek chelev,
and then here later he becomes aware they were both חלב. chelev.
Okay. So what separated it was an awareness that he was eating
ספק חלב. sofek chelev. Okay. Would that be enough to say it
was two separate
acts and he brings two קרבנות, korbanot, or would that only be
enough to say that it was, or would you still say, 'No,
since he wasn't aware he was eating definite חלב, chelev, even though
it turned out in hindsight that he was, since he wasn't aware
at the time he was eating definite חלב, chelev, did not divide
it into two separate acts.' So that's the ספק sofek whether ידיעת
ספק yedi'at sofek is it, ידיעת ספק, yedi'at sofek, is it, you
know, is it מתחלק? mit-chal-ek? Does it divide it into two separate
acts? Okay. So now, that's a question for, for in the scenario
where he became aware that they were, aware that they were whatever.
Then the question here is: how many חטאות chatatot do you bring?
Okay. And then you bring an אשם תלוי asham talui because at
some point, because you realize already... if you become aware, then the
question is one or two חטאות. chatatot. But here's another scenario. You
still don't know. You still don't know, you know. For then the
question... what did he become aware of? That it was ספק. sofek.
But you still don't know whether it definitely was. And then you
ate the other one. So then the question is: one or two
אשם תלוי? asham taluis? Okay. Now, רבי, Rebbi, רבי Rebbi said that
you bring two אשם תלוי. asham taluis. So one way of reading
רבי Rebbi is that the same way becoming, if this was definite
חלב, chelev, becoming aware that it was definite חלב chelev in the
middle would mean that it would be two קרבנות, korbanot, assuming it's
a way where you were like definitely aware and it would be
two קרבנות. korbanot. So when it is ספק חלב sofek chelev and
you become ספק sofek aware, you bring two אשם תלוי. asham taluis.
That's the easiest way of reading רבי, Rebbi, right? By analogy. If
it's ודאי חלב vadai chelev and you become ודאי vadai aware, it's
two sin offerings. If it's ספק חלב sofek chelev and you become
ספק sofek aware, it's two אשם תלוי. asham taluis. The more radical
way of reading רבי Rebbi is that in the case where it
was ספק חלב sofek chelev and you become ספק sofek aware and
in hindsight you realized it was definite חלב, chelev, this ספק sofek
would be enough to divide it for two חטאות. chatatot. So a
ספק sofek even in the case of ודאי חלב vadai chelev is
enough to divide it for two sin offerings. So certainly a ספק
sofek in the case of ספק חלב sofek chelev is going to
divide it for two אשם תלוי. asham taluis. Okay, so let's read
this. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: ואמר ריש לקיש כאן שנה רבי
ידיעות ספקות ve'amar Reish Lakish kan shanah Rebbi yedi'ot sfekot מתחלקות לחטאות
mischalkos l'chataos that even if you only doubtfully are aware right and
then later becomes clear the doubtful awareness at the time divides it
into two separate sin offerings and you would bring two separate חטאות
chataos and in the same way it's true for a חטאת, chatas,
a doubtful awareness divides, a doubtful awareness also divides for an אשם
תלוי. asham talui. That's how he reads רבי. Rebbi. רבי יוחנן אמר
Rebbi Yochanan amar no no no. כשם שידיעת ודאי, keshem she'yidiyas vadai,
it's an analogy, it's not the same. כשם שידיעת ודאי בעלמא מתחלקת
לחטאות, keshem she'yidiyas vadai b'alma mischalkes l'chataos, the same way in a
normal case becoming definitely aware divides for separate sin offerings, כך ידיעת
ספק מתחלקת לאשמות. kach yediyas safek mischalkes l'ashamos. So then being doubtfully
aware divides for different אשמות. ashamos. Very interesting two ways of reading
רבי. Rebbi. For us what's important is that רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan
says that you need definite awareness to divide it into two separate
acts, right? You got that? ידיעת ודאי yediyas vadai divides into two
separate acts. So how did רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan say in the
טומאה tumah case being aware that you are ספק טמא safek tamei
is significant? Right? Remember that case, we're going on path A, being
possibly ספק טמא, safek tamei, path B is the other. How is
being aware that you're ספק טמא safek tamei significant if רבי יוחנן
Rebbi Yochanan normally needs your a definite awareness, not a doubtful awareness?
Okay, so that's the גמרא's Gemara's question. בשלמא
דרבי יוחנן אדרבי יוחנן לא קשיא, bishlama d'Rebbi Yochanan a'Rebbi Yochanan la
kashya, I get why
רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan is not a contradiction, it sounds like it.
כאן עשו ובכל התורה כולה לא עשו. kan asu u'v'chol ha'Torah kula
lo asu. That was the emphasis of רבי יוחנן's Rebbi Yochanan's word.
Here, by the issue of טומאת מקדש, tumas mikdash, doubtful awareness is
significant, but not in other places. Now we still don't know why,
but at least he's pointing out that he's making an exception. הכא
הוא דלא כתיב ידיעה בהדיא. hacha hu d'lo kesiv yediyoh b'hedya. The
גמרא Gemara is going to tell you what the exception is. הכא
הוא דלא כתיב ידיעה בהדיא. hacha hu d'lo kesiv yediyoh b'hedya. Here
we only know about awareness because the תורה Torah says ונעלם. v'ne'elam.
So since it says ונעלם v'ne'elam it was hidden, it doesn't say
explicitly other cases the תורה Torah says והוא ידע, v'hu yada, he
knew, he should have known better, he was aware, and then he
forgot. Here it doesn't say explicitly you were aware, it just says
you forgot, we infer you were aware. So since it doesn't explicitly
say you knew, we're only inferring that, so therefore there's not as
much of an underlining of the awareness, so therefore even a doubtful
awareness suffices. The doubtful awareness again is you're aware you're definitely aware
but of what you might have done. Exactly. But then you forgot
whether you were even aware, then what? I don't know. Okay, but
you're right. You are definitely aware that you are possibly טמא. tamei.
Okay. הכא הוא דלא כתיב ידיעה בהדיא. hacha hu d'lo kesiv yediyoh
b'hedya. It doesn't say it explicitly. מוונעלם הוא דקאתי. mi'v'ne'elam hu d'ka'asi.
We're learning it out from the word ונעלם. v'ne'elam. So therefore in
this case being aware that you're doubtfully טמא, tamei, and then combining
it with another being aware that you're doubtfully טמא, tamei, right? Because
you did A and B, so one of those places you sinned,
that suffices. You don't need full you don't need awareness that you're
definite
definite. ובכל התורה כולה לא עשו u'v'chol ha'Torah kula lo asu but
they didn't do this in the rest of the תורה. Torah. דכתיב
d'kesiv elsewhere in the תורה Torah it says או הודע אליו, o
hodah eilav, it was known to him. ידיעה מעלייתא בעינן, yediyoh ma'alyas'o
ba'inan, you need full awareness. And therefore if you're aware that you
doubtfully sinned, that is not enough to be significant by other sin
offerings. It is enough in this case to be aware that you're
doubtful, to have a doubtful awareness of a doubtful state. אלא ריש
לקיש, ela Reish Lakish, but according to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, דמוקים
לה כרבי ישמעאל, d'mokim lah k'Rebbi Yishmael, rather than saying that case
of doubtful awareness by the path A and path B was רבי
ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael who doesn't require awareness at all in the
beginning, נוקמה כרבי. nukmah k'Rebbi. Why not say it's going like רבי?
Rebbi? רבי Rebbi says being aware of a doubtful state suffices. הגמרא
Gemara says קא משמע לן דרבי ישמעאל לא בעי ידיעה בתחילה. ka
mashma lan d'Rebbi Yishmael lo ba'ei yediyoh b'tchilah. Yeah, he could have
said it was רבי, Rebbi, but he wanted to make a bigger
point. He wanted to inform you that רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael does
not require
any initial awareness. That's never explicit, we're only inferring that. So ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish wanted to underscore that
point. Okay, פשיטא דלא בעי. p'shita d'lo ba'ei. Of course he doesn't.
אי דלא מיצטריך ליה קרא דונעלם דמיחייב על העלם מקדש. ei d'lo
mitztareich lei kra d'v'ne'elam d'michayev al ha'alam mikdash. No, of course he
doesn't, because he doesn't have an extra ונעלם. v'ne'elam. ונעלם v'ne'elam for
רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael tells you one tells you you forgot you
were טמא, tamei, one tells you you forgot the מקדש. mikdash. So
he doesn't have an extra ונעלם v'ne'elam to tell you that you
needed to be aware at the outset. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, just because you don't have a פסוק pasuk doesn't mean that
you don't פסקן pasken that way. מהו דתימא אי משום דלית ליה
קרא. mahu d'teima ei mishum d'leis lei kra. Maybe he doesn't infer
it from a verse, אבל מגמרא אית ליה. aval mi'gemara is lei.
Maybe he has a tradition about it. Right? It's true, like I
wouldn't have necessarily assumed he doesn't have that requirement. קא משמע לן.
ka mashma lan. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish wanted to tell you that
for רבי ישמעאל, Rebbi Yishmael, because he doesn't have an extra ונעלם,
v'ne'elam, for him you don't require to have been aware at the
beginning. It's enough that you were oblivious all throughout and then you
became aware at the end. So הדרן עלך ידיעות הטומאה. hadran alach
yediyos ha'tumah. So now we can take a deep breath and be
thankful that we are through. You all paid your dues, okay? I
don't know why there are twenty דפים dappim in a tractate that
itself is only like forty-eight forty-nine דפים dappim or whatever. Why what
was that forty percent of it was about טומאת מקדש וקדשיו. tumas
mikdash v'kodshav. I really would like to know the answer to that.
Like I said, the best I can suggest, although this is a
very weak answer I think, it was... Like I said, the best
I can suggest, although this is a very weak answer, I think
it would have been better if it had opened up the world
of נדרים. nedarim. I'll tell you why, because a נדר neder is
sort of borrows from the world of הקדש, hekdesh, and a נדר
neder you sort of create a status like this food is forbidden
to me, and this food becomes like a קרבן korban and הקדש,
hekdesh, and then I violate that, and it's like I violated הקדש.
hekdesh. There I could have seen more of a parallel with the
world of טומאת מקדש tumas mikdash and violating מקדש. mikdash. Okay, why
to do this by שבועות? shavuos? I don't know. As I said
at the outset, I think by שבועה shvua as opposed to a
נדר neder you directly invoke God's name, classic שבועה shvua is בשם
השם. beshem Hashem. So even when you don't say God's name, God's
name might be inferred. So it's sort of like you're bringing God
down on earth to testify to the veracity of the claim that
you're making or to hold you accountable for the claim that you're
making. So I do understand that there is a sort of like
divine component. But still, I mean, and you think about the מקדש,
mikdash, okay, the מקדש mikdash was the one place that God was,
you know, geographically like present on earth, you know, it's a שבועה
shvua is like as God is my witness type of a thing.
But still, I don't know, I mean, that's like a loose association.
I really don't understand why they decided to do two פרקים perakim
of טומאת מקדש. tumas mikdash. Even if they felt they needed to
say it somewhere in ש"ס, shas, like why דווקא davka to say
it here? I really still don't have an answer. Why wouldn't it
be in סדר טהרות? Seder Taharos? Yeah, well, we don't have גמרא
Gemara on סדר טהרות. Seder Taharos. But it's, but it doesn't explain
why רבי, Rebbi, who authored the משנה, Mishna, didn't put it there,
like convenient if the גמרא Gemara wanted to discuss it, the גמרא
Gemara discussed it because it was following the lead of the משנה.
Mishna. Real question is why did the משנה Mishna put it here?
And you're right, the משנה Mishna could have put it in קדשים.
kodshim. משנה Mishna could have put it elsewhere. All right, let's start
the next פרק. perek. Okay, שבועות שתים שהן ארבע. shavuos shtayim shehein
arba. So שבועות shavuos are, there are two which are four. This
is finally why we went through all that, to get to the
idea that when the תורה Torah also talks about a קרבן korban
of עולה ויורד, oleh v'yored, of a חטאת, chatas, of a sin
offering, one case is that a person made an שבועה shvua and
he violated it. Now the תורה Torah speaks about the case that
the שבועה shvua that he made was, you know, it says כי
תשבע לבטא בשפתים להרע או להיטיב, ki tishava levatei bisfasayim lehara o
lehaitiv,
to do bad or to do good, which means it's future oriented.
So the two in the תורה Torah of violating an שבועה shvua
and bringing a קרבן korban is you say you're going to do
something in the future, either a bad thing or a good thing,
which we'll sort of see means more like an active or a
passive thing. And the two and the two that become four are
when you make a claim about what you've done in the past.
Okay, so let's read that. שבועות שתים שהן ארבע, shavuos shtayim shehein
arba, שבועה שאוכל ושלא אוכל, shvua she-ochal v'she-lo ochal, I'll eat something
or I won't eat something. So that's להרע או להיטיב. lehara o
lehaitiv. To eat is to do something good because, you know, it's
taking care of your own bodily needs. To not eat is to
do something bad unless you need to go on a diet, I
don't know. שאכלתי ושלא אכלתי, she-achalti v'she-lo achalti, so those are the
two that are in the תורה. Torah. Donuts on Chanukah's good? Exactly.
שאכלתי ושלא אכלתי, she-achalti v'she-lo achalti, and when you make them past
oriented and it's about not to hold yourself to do something, but
to claim the veracity of your claim, those are the extra two,
and if you're lying about that, whatever, you bring a קרבן, korban,
or you're forgetting about that. שבועה שלא אוכל ואכל כל שהוא חייב.
shvua shelo ochal v'achal kol shehu chayav. Now, let's say you make
an שבועה shvua that you're going to eat, that you won't eat,
and you eat even a small amount, not your standard minimum size
of a כזית. kezayis. You're חייב. chayav. דברי רבי עקיבא. divrei Rebbi
Akiva. That's what רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva says. אמרו לו לרבי עקיבא,
amru lo l'Rebbi Akiva, so רבי עקיבא's Rebbi Akiva colleagues said to
him, היכן מצינו באוכל כל שהוא שחייב? heichan matzinu b'ochei kol shehu
shechayav? We've never found that even eating a tiny amount is חייב.
chayav. Why is this חייב? chayav? It's only a tiny amount שזה
חייב. sheze chayav. אמר להם רבי עקיבא, amar lahem Rebbi Akiva, וכי
היכן מצינו במדבר ומביא קרבן v'chi heichan matzinu b'medaber u-meivi korban שזה
מדבר ומביא קרבן? sheze medaber u-meivi korban? When did you ever find
somebody—so presumably here חייב chayav doesn't mean חייב chayav in lashes, by
the way, the context as we've been seeing from the beginning of
the מסכת maseches is bringing a קרבן. korban. Okay, so רבי עקיבא
Rebbi Akiva says but when do you ever bring a קרבן korban
for a speech act? So since you're bringing a קרבן korban for
a speech act, now therefore you also do a כל שהוא. kol
shehu. Now what is the relationship between a speech act and a
קרבן korban and a כל שהוא? kol shehu? Right, what does that
have to do with explaining the amount that you need to violate?
So what רבי עקיבא—so Rebbi Akiva if you look at רש"י, Rashi,
what רש"י Rashi says is, מדבר ומביא קרבן, medaber u-meivi korban, first
white line רש"י, Rashi, בשביל ביטול דיבורו. bishvil bitul diburo. The reason
he's bringing the קרבן korban is because of the speech, okay, that
he negates what he said. וכיון דמשום ביטול דיבורו הוא אף זה
ביטול דיבורו שאמר לא אוכל ודעתו לאסור עצמו בכל שהוא. v'keivan d'mishum
bitul diburo hu, af ze bitul diburo she-amar lo ochal v'daato le'esor
atzmo b'chol shehu. So רש"י Rashi switches to the question of your
intention. רש"י Rashi says because it's a question of what you said,
it's a question of what you meant. And therefore when you say
you won't eat, what that means is you won't even eat a
small amount. So it doesn't match normally by עבירות aveiros like don't
eat נבילה neveira whatever, we say that the way the תורה Torah
defines the act is a כזית. kezayis. This ultimately is rooted in
violating your word, and the sense of violating your word is rooted
in what were you intending? And therefore when you say I won't
eat a whole apple and you eat a little bit, no one
would say you... Exactly. You could say—exactly. So since you can totally
vary the amount, you're creating it, so the question all is what
did you say, and as far as what you said, it means
even a כל שהוא. kol shehu. So we're going to explore more
of that later. There might be other ways of exactly understanding the
emphasis about מדבר medaber and כל שהוא, kol shehu, okay, but that's
sort of the emphasis of the of the משנה. mishna. We will
pick up with the first גמרא. Gemara. Exactly, so since you can
totally vary the amount, you're creating it. So the question all is,
what did you say? And as far as what you said, it
means even a כל שהוא. kol shehu. So we're going to explore
more of that later. There might be other ways of exactly understanding
the emphasis about מדבר medaber and כל שהוא. kol shehu. Okay, but
that's sort of the emphasis of the משנה. mishna. We will pick
up with the first גמרא Gemara on this tomorrow.